Hi, welcome back to
Nagarjuna, course number three.
And we're going to start a new
chapter now, it's chapter 10.
And it has a great name,
and we'll see the name here.
It's called,
ME DANG BUD SHING BRTAG PA
an examination or an investigation
into fire and firewood.
And we're still getting this argument.
You see, there's still this argument that
until the young lady with the telescope
looks at the stars, we cannot
call her an astronomer.
So looking at the stars must happen
before she comes out of her house,
before the astronomer
comes out of her house.
It has to, all right?
So there's some confusion there.
And the other guy says,
"Listen, I've got a
solution, let's talk about
ME DANG BUD SHING
"let's talk about fire and firewood.
"Let's talk about fire and firewood.
"And according to me, that's
going to clarify everything.
"We will solve these problems.
If we just look at the
example of fire and firewood."
And mainly those guys like
the lower Abhidharma guys
who want to say that
the eye was there first
and then there was a scene.
The astronomer was wandering around,
and then they looked at a star,
and they were called an astronomer
even before they looked
to the stars, right?
That's their idea.
They say, "Our position is supported
by the example of fire and firewood",
the relationship between
fire and firewood.
Now to really appreciate this chapter,
I'd like to explore with you first.
Let's do our "getting to
know Sanskrit" assignment,
and let's look at four Sanskrit words
that are going to help us
understand this chapter.
The first word is "indhana", say indhana.
- [Audience] Indhana.
- Okay, the Tibetan is BUD SHING,
and this indhana comes from a root,
and you see that square
root symbol √id or √ind,
which means "to kindle" or "to set fire",
to set fire to something.
And I think it's related
to the Indo-European,
which is kind of an older
root system called √ed,
which means "to eat", and
sometimes n's drop out,
like √ind becomes √ed in
Indo-European, and it means to eat.
And some cognates or some English examples
are: edible, and eat, and obese.
And they all have the same root √ed,
which is related to the Sanskrit root √id,
which means "to burn".
The kindle part, which
means to burn something,
is related... I think it is
the precursor of a root √kand,
which means to burn.
And you see √kand in
incandescent, candle, kindle.
And I think there was an ancient S before,
which is √scand or
"schund" (pronunciation),
and that came into the word shine.
So all of these words for burning:
id, ind, ed, kand, and scand,
are all related to burning, scand,
all related to burning.
Now we were talking about
the eye looking at something,
at an object.
So Michael's eye looks at the juice.
Michael's eyes looks at the orange juice,
the orange colored juice,
and you have three distinct things.
You have the doer,
which Chоney Lama calls,
NYE BAR LEN PA PO
the agent, let's say,
the one who undertakes the action.
And then you have the
object of the action,
which is called
NYE BAR LEN PA BYA, NYE BAR LEN BYA
and then you have the
action itself, which is,
NYE BAR LEN PA
NYE BAR LEN PA PO, NYE BAR
LEN BYA and NYE BAR LEN PA
meaning the object of the action,
the agent of the action and the action,
which is seeing in this case.
Now I challenge you,
in the case of a fire,
who is the agent and who is the action?
Who is the object of the agent?
Who is the agent in the case of a fire?
And I'll give you some choices here.
Here's the first choice:
indhana, the wood.
Is the wood the agent?
Is the wood, like the eye,
which does/sees the object
because the wood feeds the fire.
There's a possibility.
Or, let's go onto the
next Sanskrit word here,
which is "agni".
And as you guys probably
know, agni means "fire"
and what's interesting is it comes
from a verbal root √ag,
which means to move
like a snake, like this.
So the flames are movers, agni.
They're dancing, dancing.
Agni means dancing. Agni means fire.
And in the Indo-European,
again you have these words for driving,
moving related to √ag that we had before.
And then you have the cognates:
act, active, agile, and agent,
all coming from the same root as √ag,
to move and get things done.
And then there's a suffix -ni,
which makes nouns out of verbs.
So agni means fire.
And in English, you
get the words "ignite",
and "igneous", meaning made from fire,
stone made from fire.
So that's the fire.
Now again, so, so far we have
firewood and we have fire.
Is it that the fire acts on the firewood
or is it that the
firewood creates the fire?
Which is the agent?
With the eye it's easy,
the eye sees the bottle.
The bottle is the object,
the seeing is the verb,
and the eye is the subject.
But in the case of a fire, who
is the doer and what is done?
Is the fire the result of the wood,
or is it that the fire acts on the wood?
Is the wood the object of the fire,
or is the wood the agent of the fire?
You've got to think about it.
It's confusing, to me it's confusing.
Okay, let's do a couple more words.
And then we'll get to the real class.
Dāha, say dāha.
- [Audience] Dāha.
- Okay, and that means
SREG PA, it means burning.
The burning.
So the fire burns the
wood. Can we say that?
Or the wood feeds the fire?
But anyway, √dah is the root
here, which means to burn.
I think it's related to "daha",
and then "dh" is sometimes
changed into the F in English,
which is F, and then to make it an agent,
you have to call it a "fa-er",
and then I think fire.
And a parallel case is where
√dhr, which became dharma,
which means to hold something,
it comes into the word "firm".
And it's also the root
for the word "tree",
because trees were the
most immovable thing
in the ancient world.
You couldn't move a tree.
So there you go, √dhr and √dah.
One more word for you guys:
in this chapter, they're
going to talk about
fire burning wood
until the wood is used
up and then the fire,
here's the next word, nirvana.
Isn't that interesting?
So you always hear about nirvana,
meaning "to blow out" [blows] a candle,
but here in Nagarjuna, in this chapter,
he's using it without
reference to liberation.
It just means the fire went out, nirvana.
It blew itself out.
It burned itself out. The
fire burned itself out.
So nirvana. And by the
way the V in Sanskrit
is more of... almost like a W (nirwana).
The Tibetan is,
MYANG NGAN LAS 'DAS PA
which is a meaning translation
and not literal translation,
which means to go beyond grief.
And here's the parts of the word nirvana,
which I want you to learn.
Nis- is a prefix, which means "not".
And it means "out and down",
meaning something
degenerates until it's gone.
And then you have the
words nether, beneath,
and underneath
comes from this.
√van means to blow.
That's an easy one for English cognates:
you have fan, vent and wind.
So blow out [blows] is nirvana.
I think it's exciting in this chapter
that we see nirvana used
only as a fire being blown out.
And that gives you a nice insight
into the idea of blowing out
your anger at your husband,
because you realize it's coming from you.
That's nirvana.
All right, let's go back to the beginning
of this chapter ten.
And we're going to go through
the verses one by one.
Now the first verse is
traditionally split into two.
The first verse is traditionally treated
first two Tibetan lines, and
then second two Tibetan lines.
And by the way, the Sanskrit still exists,
which is exciting. If you
want to learn Sanskrit,
this book is a great text
to learn Sanskrit from.
I don't emphasize learning Sanskrit
because most of the Sanskrit is gone.
So whereas in Tibetan
you have maybe 500,000 important books.
In Sanskrit you have a few hundred, maybe.
So, I don't know if it's worth the effort
to spend six, seven
years learning Sanskrit.
The Tibetan is exactly
the same as the Sanskrit.
I rarely, rarely, rarely
see any difference.
All right, here we go.
First half of the first verse.
,BUD SHING GANG DE ME YIN NA,
,BYED PA PO DANG LAS GCIG 'GYUR,
Now the first... the way that Nagarjuna
explores the other guy's example,
The other guy says,
"Look, you can understand all
your questions, Nagarjuna,
"if you just use the example
of a fire and the firewood,
"and the interaction of
the fire and the firewood,
"you're getting all complicated,
"you don't have to do it."
If you just think about how
a fire consumes firewood,
then everything's clear.
The discussion of whether the little girl
had to be there first,
or that looking at the
stars had to be there first,
and then the little girl
was an astronomer later,
the whole discussion is
decided by fire and firewood.
Just stick to fire and firewood.
And Nagarjuna says, "Not really."
He's like, "I don't think so."
- Well, what's wrong with that, Nagarjuna?
- Well, is the fire separate
from the firewood or not?
Is the fire a separate
thing than the firewood?
What do you guys think?
I mean, okay, listen, Nagarjuna says,
"Listen, either the firewood is the fire
"or the firewood is not
the fire. Which one?"
And he says, "Okay, let's say
"you say they are the same
thing. Well, they're not."
I mean, you can't burn
yourself on the firewood
if it's not.
So let's eliminate one
possibility from the beginning.
We can say that the
firewood is not the fire.
They're not the same thing.
So here it says,
BUD SHING GANG DE ME YIN NA
if the firewood were the fire,
BYED PA PO DANG LAS GCIG 'GYUR
then the agent, then the
burner and the burning
would be the same thing.
The burning would be the burner.
If you take the wood to
be the cause of the fire,
then the wood would be the burning.
Then the wood would be the burning.
It's not possible that the fire
and the wood are the same thing.
So let's eliminate that possibility.
Let's go on to the
possibility that the fire
and the wood are not the same thing,
and that they're separate.
Okay, we go to the second
half of the first...
Oh and by the way, that picture,
we missed a picture here,
I was supposed to explain a picture here:
people looking at a campfire.
And I don't know, where
I grew up in Arizona,
it's very popular to go out in the desert
and make a small fire. Small
fire, not this big one.
And you sit around the campfire
and you look at the fire.
So the guy says, the other guy says,
"Look, what the eye does
when it looks at a star
"is not unreal. It's real."
Meaning for him it's self-existent.
It comes from its own side. Why?
Because the- fire and
what it burns are real.
So he says, "When
somebody looks at a star,
"it's really happening
"because it's really happening
"when fire burns wood same thing."
RIGS PA MGO MTSUNGS
means parallel reasoning.
Okay, next verse, second part of...
Oh, by the way, one more
picture before the...
Nagarjuna says, "If the fire was the wood,
"then the person making a pot out of clay
"would be the pot."
All right?
And that's easy to understand.
It's one of the few easy
things to understand
in Nagarjuna.
That's clear: if the fire was a firewood,
then this girl would be a pot.
Then what makes the
thing would be the thing.
If the fire is the wood that it burns,
then the potter is the pot that it makes.
And this girl would be a pot.
And this girl would be
in this girl's own hands
or something like that.
Not possible.
Let's go to the second half
of the first verse.
anyaś ced indhanād agnir
indhanād apy ṛte bhavet
,GAL TE SHING LAS ME GZHAN NA,
If the wood is not the fire,
if the wood and the fire are separate,
Now you've got to think of...
Here's a principle when
you're reading Nagarjuna.
Is the fire separate from the wood or not?
Yeah, it's separate from the wood.
Is it self-existently
separate from the wood?
You see, now, because Nagarjuna
is going to keep pulling out this word,
self-existently, without an observer,
with karmic seeds in their mind,
is the wood separate from the fire?
And Nagarjuna says,
"No, they're not separate
from their own side."
So you have to remember that.
GAL TE SHING LAS ME GZHAN NA
If the wood was distinct from the fire,
then they would not overlap.
They would never make contact.
When I say overlap, I mean make contact.
- Geshe-la, it is not the same thing.
To touch something and
to overlap is different.
- Look, here's contact
and here's overlapping.
But you've got to understand
that if they make contact,
some part has to overlap.
Some part has to overlap. Why?
There has to be a point of contact.
In mathematics, a point is a single spot
that has no width and no length.
But in reality, if something touches,
there has to be a point of contact.
There has to be so many
millimeters of place
where they overlap,
where they occupied the same spot,
or you couldn't have contact.
There can't be contact.
So he says, "If the fire and
the wood never make contact,"
meaning they are separate,
if they are different from each other,
if they never made contact,
well, then you're going
to have fires popping out
all over the place where there's no wood.
- Oh, keep away, there's
a fire right there!"
- What? There's no wood.
- Yeah, you don't need wood.
- Why?
- It's separate.
They don't have to touch.
There doesn't have to be wood in the room
for a fire to break out.
- Why?
Because all fires happen.
- What do you mean all fires happen?
- Fires happen where there's wood, right?
- Yeah.
- So they touch, right?
- No, they can't touch.
- Why not?
- They can't overlap.
- Okay, so they're separate,
what's the problem with that?
- Well, then you can
have a fire in this room
if you had firewood in the next room.
Because they don't have to touch.
If they don't have to overlap
then the fire could be anywhere
and the wood could be anywhere.
Then you'd have fires breaking
out all over the place.
- No, no, no, they have to touch.
- Okay, if they have to touch
they have to make contact.
- Yeah, then they have to overlap.
- Right.
- Then the fire is the wood.
- No. - Look, you can't have it both ways.
Nagarjuna is like pulling his hair out.
That's what happened to me.
If they make contact,
then some tiny part of the
fire has to be the firewood.
- No, I don't want that.
- Okay, so they never make contact.
- Right.
- Okay, so then watch out,
you've got to have a fire
extinguisher in your toilet,
for your toilet,
because the fire might
pop out in the toilet.
- No there's water there, Geshe-la.
- I don't care, a fire
can happen anywhere,
it doesn't have to touch a wood.
If you're not confused yet,
I didn't do my job. Next verse.
And he combines verse two and verse three.
Who is he? Choney Lama.
,RTAG TU 'BAR BA NYID DU 'GYUR,
,'BAR BYED RGYU LAS MI 'BYUNG ZHING,
,RTZOM PA DON MED NYID DU 'GYUR,
,DE LTA YIN NA LAS KYANG MED,
Okay, RTAG TU 'BAR BA NYID DU 'GYUR
Not only would fires break
out inside your toilet,
they would also burn forever. Why?
Because they don't burn from the wood.
They just burn from themselves,
because the wood never touches the fire.
- No, the fire does touch the wood.
- Okay, then they overlap, right?
And the wood is the fire and
the fire is the wood, right?
At some point.
- No, no they're separate.
- Okay, then watch out,
when you take a poop causes you a fire,
the water might catch on fire.
[Geshe Michael chuckles]
- Well, I didn't say that.
- Yeah, you did. You said
a fire could happen without firewood.
- I didn't say that.
- Yeah, you did,
you said it didn't have
to touch the firewood.
- Yeah, I did say that.
- Okay, so the fire can
be in the other room,
the fire can be in the toilet.
Be careful when you take a poop.
Okay. Something else is
going on, something's fishy.
What's going on?
Maybe a separate entity is
causing the fire in the firewood.
And maybe the firewood has
nothing to do with the fire.
And maybe the mantra has nothing to do
with curing the cancer.
Maybe they're both coming
from somewhere else.
RTAG TU 'BAR BA NYID DU 'GYUR
Then not only would your
toilet break out on in fire,
but RTAG TU
means it would never go out,
because there's no wood.
It just burns by itself.
'BAR BYED RGYU LAS MI 'BYUNG ZHING
Furthermore, you could have
fires without any fuel.
RTZOM PA DON MED NYID DU 'GYUR
And you wouldn't have
to go through the effort
of collecting firewood
because you could have a fire
without the firewood.
So why go through all the
trouble of finding firewood
or buying oil for your
car, gasoline for your car?
Because it's going to
burn without the gasoline.
The engine is going to
Then he gives another
verse. And I was confused
when I first read it
because it seems like he
repeats the same thing.
But I tell you, if you
look at it carefully,
you will see that verse three
is a justification of verse two.
And you can cook that
and you can work on that.
GZHAN LA LTOS PA MED PA'I PHYIR
If the fire didn't depend on the wood,
then yes, fires could break out everywhere
and they would go forever.
'BAR BAR BYED RGYU LAS MI 'BYUNG
And the fires would go for always
because they didn't have to have fuel.
RTAG TU 'BAR BA YIN NA NI
They will also burn forever
because they didn't have fuel,
and the fuel can't run out.
RTZOM PA DON MED NYID DU 'GYUR
And you wouldn't have
to go collect firewood
or buy gasoline for your engine to run.
And that's similar to the assertion
that the eye wouldn't have to depend,
the eyeball wouldn't have
to depend on its causes,
because it had no connection to them.
And it wouldn't be the cause of seeing.
Because the seeing and the eyeball
and the chemicals in the eye were separate
and never overlapped.
You've got to think about it.
He's really making the same argument
that he made in the last
chapter, which is the point
because this chapter is
used by the other guy
to prove his points in the last chapter.
So don't forget when we're
talking about fire and firewood,
we're really talking about the eye,
the astronomer, and the stars.
All right... And the sun
would really burn forever.
Here's the sun.
If the fuel, the hydrogen,
that makes the sun burn,
and the sun were separate,
then the sun would never burn out,
because it has no fuel.
You would just have this
fire going on forever.
And this sun would never burn out.
The Abhidharma says our
sun is going to burn out.
And Stephen Hawkins says the same thing.
So probably he was an
Abhidharma guy, I don't know.
All right, next verse.
,DE LA GAL TE 'DI SNYAM DU,
,SREG BZHIN BUD SHING YIN SEMS NA,
,GANG TSE DE TZAM DE YIN NA,
,GANG GIS BUD SHING DE SREG BYED,
And by the way, this is
a... what do you call it?
This is a method employed
by Nagarjuna again:
he will disprove something
that somebody else said,
then he kind of gives the other
guy a chance to come back,
and then he smashes him.
So he punches him with the first verse.
The guy comes back. And then
the Nagarjuna knocks him out
with the second verse. So it's called
MA NGES PA SPANG BA
It means Nagarjuna is nailing it down.
So then this verse is kind of
the same as the last verse,
but it's meant to knock
the guy out forever.
The first one just
punched him. Here we go.
DE LA GAL TE 'DI SNYAM DU
And now suppose you think to yourself,
he says to the other guy,
SREG BZHIN BUD SHING YIN SEMS NA
the burning is the wood.
Don't forget we had fire, agni.
We had firewood, indhana.
We had burning, daha.
And then this guy... now the
guy says, "You know what?
The burning is the wood."
The burning is wood.
They are not separate.
And frankly, his example
of a fire is controversial.
It's difficult to thresh
it out in our own mind
because really when a piece
of wood is really burning,
it's kind of hard to distinguish
between where the fire ends
and where the wood starts.
,`GANG TSE DE TZAM DE YIN NA,
,GANG GIS BUD SHING DE SREG BYED,
If the burning is the firewood
then what burns the firewood,
except for the firewood?
Does the firewood burn the firewood?
That's Nagarjuna.
I'll say it again.
That guy says, "You know what?
"If you really thinks about it,
"the fire and the firewood
are kind of mixed up."
And then Nagarjuna says, "Yeah, cool.
"So the firewood burns the firewood,
"and you don't need the fire.
"Because the firewood is the burning."
He said, "The burning and the firewood
"are kind of mixed up."
So Nagarjuna said, "Yeah, that's fine.
"So just put a couple of sticks together,
"and they can burn each
other without fire,
"because the one stick is already mixed up
"with the fire."
Like that.
All right, the burning of the
wood couldn't burn the wood.
What's the picture, Pachi?
Oh, that's why the boy
is looking confused.
He just heard this verse.
[Geshe Michael chuckles]
If the burning was the fire...
if the burning was the firewood,
then, one match could burn another match
without a fire, got it?
That's why the boy is looking confused.
All right, this boy represents you guys.
[Geshe Michael laughs]
Next verse.
- And what's it got to do with mantra?
- Oh, saying the Mantra
is curing the cancer.
- Okay, so then curing the cancer
is caused by curing the cancer,
and you don't have to do a mantra.
Because curing the cancer is the mantra.
The mantra is curing the cancer.
The mantra cures the cancer.
- Okay, so curing the
cancer is curing the cancer,
and you don't need a
mantra, you can just relax.
Okay, got it?
The mantra is curing the cancer.
- Okay.
- Then you don't need a mantra.
- Why?
- Because curing the
cancer can cure the cancer.
- Why?
- Because the mantra is curing the cancer.
Okay, got it?
All right. By the way, if
you don't think about it
and you just give up,
you won't be able to use mantras.
So I'm sorry, you have to
think about this stuff.
You have to go into retreat
at Diamond Mountain,
in your spare time think about this thing.
And then you'll figure it out.
One day you'll figure it out.
And then the mantra will work,
qhich is exciting
And by the way, I mean,
it's going to take time.
- Oh Geshe-la, should I stop my mantras
until I can understand Nagarjuna?
- I didn't say that.
Keep doing the mantras,
they're going to help
you understand Nagarjuna.
And then understanding Nagarjuna
will have the mantras work.
Verse five I think.
,GZHAN PHYIR MI PHRAD PHRAD MED NA,
,SREG PAR MI 'GYUR MI SREG NA,
,'CHI BAR MI 'GYUR MI 'CHI NA,
,RANG RTAGS DANG YANG LDAN PAR GNAS,
GZHAN PHYIR MI PHRAD
- Okay, does the fire...
is the fire the firewood?
- We already said no.
- Okay, so the fire and the
firewood is separate, right?
- Yeah, they're separate.
- Okay, and they can't overlap, right?
- Right, they cannot overlap.
- Why?
- There cannot be an inch of
the fire which is the firewood.
Either all the fire is the firewood
or the fire is not the firewood.
They've got to be separate.
- Are they separate?
- Yes.
- Do they ever overlap?
- No.
- Okay, so then the fire
can't burn the wood.
- Why?
- It never touches the wood.
- No, they do touch.
- Okay, then they overlap.
- Okay. Then the firewood is the fire.
- Right.
- Then the firewood can burn the firewood,
and you don't need a match?
It's true.
It doesn't make sense, there's
something weird going on.
You just never thought about it.
Don't blame Nagarjuna.
The things you used to
think were causing things,
aren't causing things, but you
spend your whole life lazy,
not thinking about it.
And you keep taking aspirin,
even though it doesn't work half the time.
All right. And you keep doing mantras,
even though they don't work half the time.
GZHAN PHYIR MI PHRAD PHRAD MED NA
If the fire never touches the firewood
and they never overlap,
SREG PAR MI 'GYUR
there cannot be a burning.
If the fire, if the agni
never touches the indhana
Right? There cannot be a daha.
If the agni never touches the indhana,
then there can never be a daha.
If the fire never touches the firewood,
then there cannot be a burning.
And if there's no burning,
there's no nirvana.
What does that mean?
[indistinct Chattering]
If there's no fire, then there's
no fire going out, nirvana.
And this is where the word nirvana comes.
If there's no fire, if
the firewood never...
if the fire never touches the firewood,
then there's not going to be any fire.
And if there's no fire to start,
then the fire is never
going to stop. Nirvana.
Then if it never stops, MI 'CHI NA
MI 'CHI NA, which in the
Sanskrit is anirvāṇa (anirvana).
If there's no stopping of the fire,
RANG RTAGS DANG YANG LDAN PAR GNAS
then the fire is going to be hot forever
because burning is part of the fire
and it can never go out
and it can never start.
So every time something is a fire
it's going to burn forever.
It's just going to burn.
It will never lose its
svalinga
in Sanskrit, "linga" means its sign.
By the way, which means a
male sign and a female sign.
But in philosophy it means
the fire would never
lose his hot and burning.
And it would burn forever.
svalinga
It would keep it's own sign forever.
- Why?
- Because it never went out.
- Because it never burned.
- Why?
- Because the fire never
touched the firewood.
Something you've got to cook.
All right, we did the
Sanskrit part already,
let's go... Yeah, and by the way,
Nagarjuna wraps it up and says,
"By the way, if the fire
could burn the firewood
without any contact, then you could...",
next picture Pachi? Tim?
"...then a match will light a cigarette
without ever touching the cigarette."
The fire doesn't have
to touch the cigarette.
If a fire could happen without overlapping
between the fire and the firewood,
then somebody could start
a lighter in Guadalajara
and the cigarette will burn in Sedona.
Because they don't have to
touch, according to you.
All right, we don't want to smoke anyway.
I felt weird about it.
Next two verses, six and seven.
Now, this is one of those
tricky spots in Nagarjuna.
Verse six is the other guy
and verse seven is Nagarjuna.
But he doesn't tell you.
Now when you get really
good at reading scripture,
you know which verse is fake
and which verse is right.
But if you don't, you better
get a good commentary.
I've heard many people explain
the other guy's position
as Nagarjuna's position, very eloquently.
And it's just totally wrong.
By the way, in my opinion,
I'm not aware of any good
translation of the root text,
I don't think so. Correct
one - I don't think so.
,JI LTAR BUD MED SKYES PA DANG,
,SKYES PA'ANG BUD MED PHRAD PA BZHIN,
,GAL TE SHING LAS ME GZHAN NA,
,SHING DANG PHRAD DU RUNG BAR 'GYUR,
The other guy says,
"Look, when a man touches a woman
"and a woman touches a
man, they're different."
What is the -
Vive la différence -
A woman is not a man,
and a man is not a woman.
And that's the only reason they can touch.
If they were the same thing,
then they would never touch.
And then we wouldn't be here
because our mom and our dad
would not have touched each other, right?
So he says,
"Look, women touch men
and men touch women.
"And it's only if the firewood
and the fire are separate
"that you could have
touching between them."
Things can't touch if
they're not different.
A thing doesn't touch
itself. You see what I mean?
A coffee cup can't touch a coffee cup.
This coffee cup doesn't
touch this coffee cup
because it's not different
from this coffee cup.
This coffee cup is not
different from this coffee cup,
so they could never make contact
because they're the same thing.
To have contact, things
have to be different.
And then they can contact each other.
Therefore, come on, it's simple.
It's like boys and girls.
And then they touch, they're different.
So the fire and the firewood,
they have to be different things.
The other guy says,
"I don't know why you're
getting it so complicated."
That's verse number six, am I right? Yeah.
Now, verse number seven is our answer.
Nagarjuna's answer.
,GAL TE ME DANG SHING DAG NI,
,GCIG GIS GCIG NI BSAL GYUR NA,
,SHING LAS ME GZHAN NYID YIN YANG,
,SHING DANG PHRAD PAR 'DOD LA RAG,
Now we go back to that verb we had
where one thing illuminates another thing,
or one thing delineates another thing.
And he says, you know what?
,GAL TE ME DANG SHING DAG NI,
,GCIG GIS GCIG NI BSAL GYUR
"Is it that juice bottles
define coffee cups,
and coffee cups define juice bottles?"
Is it that women define
men, and men define women?
In that case, they have
to be separate, right?
If they "touch"... By the way,
the other guy was talking about touching
in the sense of physically
touching each other,
but Nagarjuna takes it to, "Okay.
So, you can't really tell a man is a man
until he's in a room with a woman."
You can't distinguish male without female.
In that sense, they have to touch,
meaning they have to
be in the same picture.
We've got a picture here, I think so.
Male and female have
to be in the same photo
to appreciate the difference
between a man and a woman.
They have to be in the same photo.
And then you can say, oh,
look, he's got a beard,
she doesn't have a beard.
She's got lipstick, he doesn't have that.
I don't know exactly, but...
So when they're in the same photo,
when the juice bottle is
next to the coffee cup,
then you can tell the
contrast defines each one.
Each one defines the other.
When you put them in the
same frame of your camera,
your video right now.
When you put them in the same frame,
then this one speaks to the
difference between that one,
and this one speaks to the
difference from that one.
,GAL TE ME DANG SHING DAG NI,
,GCIG GIS GCIG NI BSAL GYUR NA,
Are you saying they define each other?
Yes, okay.
,SHING LAS ME GZHAN NYID YIN YANG,
,SHING DANG PHRAD PAR 'DOD LA RAG,
Then you have to say they make contact.
'DOD -  'DOD PA
You have to be believe they make contact.
- Do they make contact?
- Yes.
- Do they overlap?
- No.
- Do they make contact
without overlapping?
- Yes.
- Where's the point of contact?
- It's where they overlap.
[Geshe Michael chuckles]
- So don't tell me that
males define females
and females define males,
because they can't touch.
- No, they have to touch
to define each other.
- That's correct, so they have to overlap.
- No Geshe-la, they touch
without overlapping.
- Okay, so there's no point
where they touch, right?
There's no point where
one overlaps the same area
with the other, which
is what contact means.
Get used to that.
It's not that there's a tiny
tip of the male that...well...
It's not that there's a
tiny tip of the bottle
that touches a tiny tip of the coffee cup.
At some point they have to overlap.
Or else they don't touch, and
then they are disconnected.
And you can't say one
is defined by the other.
You can't say one is delineated,
@adhyate,
by the other, you can't say that.
It's very subtle, and
if you think about it,
you'll get it.
Don't give up, don't be lazy.
You want to cure
someone's cancer with your
Medicine Buddha mantras?
You've got to figure this out.
And I say, if you don't understand this,
you cannot cure another
person with your mantras
because then you don't
know what you're doing.
Then you're yelling at the
husband who's not in the kitchen.
Doing mantras, without
understanding them, to cure cancer
is like yelling at the
husband in the kitchen
who's not there.
It's a same thing.
Woah! Okay, yeah, we've got that one.
Hey, we finished the class! Yay!
So think about it.
Can they touch without overlapping?
No.
Well, if they overlap,
then they don't touch,
then they're the same thing.
Then the man is the woman,
and a little part of him is the woman.
And they don't define each other.
And the point is, for us, a
mantra cannot cure cancer,
if the mantra doesn't touch the cancer
and the mantra cannot touch the cancer.
- So Geshe-la, why the
heck should I do mantras?
- Because there's one
thing causing the mantra,
which also causes the curing.
- Well, what's that?
- That's saving life of animals.
Saving the life of the animals
makes the mantra work to cure
cancer. Think about that.
All right, see you guys
in the next class, yay!